Let us now discuss the different types of noise that we can have in an image or a
我们来讨论一下在图像或视频中出现的不同种类的噪声
video. normally, the way we do that is we
通常情况下
basically define what's the probability of the noise taking certain value.
我们会根据特定的概率来定义不同类型的噪声
Remember, we are talking about adding noise to the image as we discussed in the
还记得吧 我们在上一个视频中提到过 图像中会掺入噪声
previous video. So let's just start with Gaussian noise
那么我们先从高斯噪声 (Gaussian noise) 开始
and I'm going to write down the formula for it.
我来写一下它的公式
So the probability of a certain value, this is a function that you have probably
所以某个值的概率 这个方程大家可能见过很多次了
seen a large number of times already, is 1 over square root of 2 pi sigma.
即1除以根号2π和σ的积
That's basically, we are getting, they are the standard deviation of the
这是噪声的标准差
noise. The exponent of minus c minus average.
再乘以底数e 指数是负的 z减去z的平均值
We see it here, the average of the noise, square, that's very important, divided by
我们这里看到的就是噪声的平均值 记得取平方 这是非常重要的
2 sigma square, the variants of the noise.
再除以2乘以σ的平方 即噪声的方差
So this is the formula for Gaussian noise and we see it's function here.
所以这就是高斯噪声的公式 我们可以看到它的函数是这样的
Now, you might ask yourself, are there any real systems than, let's say when I
现在 大家可能会自问 是否存在这样的实际系统
take an image, what I see is additive Gaussian noise?
比如说拿到一个图像 上面是加性高斯噪声？
And unfortunately it's not, actually there's not real physical systems that
很不幸没有这样的例子 没有任何实际存在的系统
produce Gaussian noise. So, why is this such an important noise?
会产生高斯噪声 那么为什么这是如此重要的噪声呢？
This is probably the most used noise model in most of image and video
这很可能是在图像和视频处理系统中最广为应用的噪声模型
processing systems for a couple of reasons.
原因有几点
One of them, because mathematically, is very easy to work with and we are going
原因之一 就是这在数学上是非常容易操作的
to see that later during this, this few weeks of, of image and video processing
这点我们在剩下几周的图像和视频处理课程中会看到
classes. And also, because it's a good
另外一个原因 这是一个
approximation to other types of noise, especially when we look at small regions
对其他类型噪声很好的近似 尤其是当我们关注
of the image or small region of pixel values.
图像中的一小块区域或者一小块区域中的像素值时
So it's very powerful and you're going to see most of the literature in image and
所以这是非常强大的 并且你们会看到 大部分关于图像和视频处理的文献中
video processing addressing Gaussian noise.
都涉及有关高斯噪声的内容
And once again, here, we have the mean, the average,
再提醒一下 这里是均值 也就是平均数
and here we have the variance of, of the noise.
这里是噪声的方差
Okay? So that's Gaussian.
这就是高斯噪声
Now, let's just talk about Rayliegh noise.
下面我们来讲瑞利噪声 (Rayleigh Noise)
In contrast with Gaussian, this actually does appear in real physical systems and
和高斯噪声相比 瑞利噪声是会出现在实际系统中的
let's just write a formula for it. It's a big longer, but bear with me.
现在我们来写一下它的公式 这个公式会比较长 大家来耐心看一下
So the probability of a certain value. We're going to decompose it in two parts.
某个值的概率 我们要把它分解成两个部分
One is 2 / b and there is a few parameters as we see here,
一部分是 2/b 这里有一些参数
2 / b, z - a,
2/b 乘以z-a
e minus, z - a^2 as we have for the Gaussian, over b.
再乘上e的 负(z-a)的平方 次方 这和高斯噪声的公式相似 再除以b
Now, that's the value that the function assumes if z is greater or equal than a
如果z大于或等于a 函数值由这个方程决定
and is actually 0 if z is less or equal pictures, basically less than a.
如果z小于等于a 那么函数值就等于0
Okay? So, it looks like a complicated formula.
这看起来是一个很复杂的公式
It has this quadratic exponential, the same as in the Gaussian, it's multiplied
这里有二次的指数 和高斯噪声一样
by this and there's two parameters, b and a.
再乘上这部分 这里有两个参数 b 和 a
And let me write down two important things before I describe you examples of
在我给大家举几个瑞利噪声的例子之前 先写下两个重要的值
the Rayleigh, Rayliegh noise. One is the average,
一个是平均值
it's not hard to compute, that the average of this is a plus square
这并不难算出 它的平均值是 a 加上 πb/4 的平方根
root of pi b over four. So that's the average of the signal if we have that
这就是瑞利噪声信号的平均值
type of noise. And the variance of the signal, of the sigma, of the signal I
而该信号的方差 σ
apologize, is b(4 - pi) / 4. Okay?
抱歉 信号的方差是 b(4-π)/4
So these are for you, just formulas, and you know, simple models of the noise.
这里就是几个简单的噪声模型的公式
Now, this noise normally is used to model, for example, noise in certain
这个噪声通常用于模拟 比如说
areas of, of magnetic resonant imaging. So, in contrast with the Gaussian noise
磁共振图像中的某些区域 因此与高斯噪声相比
that is extremely good for us to basically do some math and do some nice
高斯噪声是方便计算和做一些很好的还原
restoration, but it's not really appearing in real
但却没有在任何实际的设备中出现
physical devices. This is a good model for real physical
这是一个很好的实际设备噪声模型
devices. As I say, for example, the magnetic
正如我说过的 比如 磁共振
resonance is also used in under water imaging.
这也被用在水下成像上
So there are many different disciplines, that basically the Rayleigh is a very,
在很多不同的应用领域中 瑞利噪声是一个
very good model for, for that, for, for, basically the noise appearing in those
对于这些设备中产生的噪声非常非常好的模拟
devices. Let's just, you have the gamma noise
这里是伽马噪声 (gamma noise)
here, the formula. Let's just talk about exponential noise.
及其公式 下面我们来讲一下指数噪声 (exponential noise)
In the exponential noise, so once again, I just start by writing the formula.
在指数噪声中 我还是先来写出它的公式
The probability of z of basically a certain value of the noise is once again,
z 或者说某一噪声值的概率
and this is going to be very important in a second,
这个公式在之后的课程中非常重要
e to the, is a, e to the minus az when z is positive, 0
当z是正数时 其概率值是a乘以e的负az次方
when z is negative. So, basically, the Rayleigh noise was
当z为负数时概率是0 所以瑞利噪声是不对称的
nonsymmetric, but the exponential, basically,
而指数噪声
there was no noise. Basically, there is no negative values
这里没有噪声 也就是没有负的噪声值
of, of noise and that's a very important property.
这是一个非常重要的特性
Once again, the average, not hard to compute, is 1 /
再来算平均值 并不难算出 是1/a
a, and then sigma square is 1 / a^2.
而σ的平方 是1除以a的平方
And you can have different numbers here depending on your scaling,
我们可以在这里根据比例取不同的值
a is just a scaling. So this is the exponential noise.
a只是比例因子 这就是指数噪声
Another popular noise, but I'm going to discuss the, when, can we see this
它也是一个常用的噪声 但是我们先讨论下一个噪声
exponential noise? Actually, when I describe next the
那我们什么时候会看到指数噪声？ 就在我等一下讲解
uniform noise. So let me just first write the formulas
均匀噪声 (uniform noise) 的时候 让我先写出均匀噪声的公式
for the uniform noise, ask you a couple of questions about that, and then explain
问大家一些相关问题 并解释
worries that we actually see this type of, of noise. So let's just write the
什么情况下会出现这种噪声 现在我们先写一下
forumula for the uniform noise, the uniform noise is basically saying that
均匀噪声的公式 那就是
there is noise of exactly the same value between these two. No noise outside and
在这两个值之间噪声值完全一致 区域外没有噪声
once you are inside, all the noise has basically is uniform, as the, as the name
一旦进入这个区域 所有噪声都是均匀的 正如它的名字一样
says. So the probability is once again 1 / b-a if you are in this interval.
因此在这个区间内概率为1/(b-a)
So basically, a less wqual than c, less equal than b.
这里的区间是a≤z≤b
0 if you're outside of the interval. So I'm going to write other.
在这个区间外概率为0 这里我写成其他 (other)
Basically, you're outside of the interval.
也就是在区间外的时候
So, uniform inside the interval 0 outside of the interval.
这就是区间内均匀分布 区间外为0
So let me ask you a question. What's the average for this noise?
让我来问你一个问题 这个噪声的平均值是多少？
So look at this picture or if you want, do the math on the side and tell me,
来看一下这张图 或者自己算一下 并告诉我
what's the average of this noise. Okay?
这个噪声的平均值是多少
I'm going to give you, in the quiz, a number of possibilities.
我会在题目中给大家一些选项
And I'm going to respond to that in just one second.
过一会儿我会解释这个答案
So what's the average here? Very easy to compute.
这里的平均值是多少 这非常好算
The average here is a + b / 2. So that's the average.
平均值是 (a+b)/2 这就是平均值
So if I'm having uniform noise, that's the average of my noise.
如果我有均匀噪声 这就是噪声的平均值
Okay? And how much is sigma squared?
那么σ的平方是多少呢？
You're going to have that as one of your homework, as one of your quizzes for, for
这会是大家的作业 在第四周的测试中会出现
week 4. Now, when do we see this type of noise?
那么 我们什么时候会看到这种噪声
For example, this is a very good model. Actually, both of them are good models
比如 这是一个非常好的模型 实际上 这两个都是对量化噪声
for quantization noise. Okay?
非常好的模型
So, if you remember, in the, mostly in the first week, but also in the second
如果大家还记得 主要在第一周 第二周也有
week, when we discussed image compression, we talked about
当我们提到图像压缩时 我们讲到了量化
quantization. And the basic idea in quantization is that we had a range of
量化的基本思想是 对于一个范围的值
values and we represented it by a quantized value,
我们用一个量化值来表示它们
let's say, the point in the middle. So when you actually obtain this value,
比如 中间的这一点 所以当大家取这个值时
you actually represent it with a point in the middle,
其实是用这个中间的值表示的
so you're making this noise. If you get this value,
因此产生了这个噪声 如果取这个值
you are making this noise. And that type of noise very often is
那么就产生了这个噪声 这种噪声
modeled as uniform noise inside this interval.
通常用在这个区间内的均匀噪声来模拟
There's no noise outside that interval, because when you're quantizing, you
这里在这个区间外没有噪声 因为当我们量化时
define an interval, and then you define, basically, the
就会定义一个区间 然后我们会定义
representative of that interval. So uniform noise is a model for
这个区间的量化值 所以均匀噪声是
quantization noise and that teaches us something new, a new concept.
量化噪声的一个模型 这教给我们一个新的概念
Noise sometimes comes from the device. Let's say, the sensors in our cameras.
噪声有时是从设备中产生的 比如相机中的传感器
Noise, sometimes comes because of an operation that we do to images.
有时噪声的产生是源于我们对图像的操作
And beautiful noise is a good model to this quantization operation.
而均匀噪声是关于这个量化操作很好的模型
Exponential noise sometimes is also used as a good model for this quantisation,
指数噪声有时也用作这个量化的模型
but it's also the type of noise or error when we do predictive coding.
当我们做预测编码时也会产生这种噪声或者误差
Remember, in predictive coding, when we're trying to predict a pixel,
记得在预测编码中 当我们试图估计一个像素值时
let's say, from it's surrounding pixels. So, what's the value of this pixel if I
比如 用它周围的像素进行估计 那么 如果我告诉大家这些像素值
tell you all this? That's what we did for predictive coding.
中间这个像素值是多少呢？ 这就是预测编码中我们做的事
The error of that prediction is normally more than as an exponential error or an
这个预测的误差通常是比指数误差或指数噪声大的
exponential noise. For example, the JPEG or less standard,
比如 在火星车上用到的
which is basically used in the Mars Rover uses this model for the error of the
JPEG-LS (无损图像压缩) 标准 就用到了这个模型处理预测列的误差
predictive column. So very interesting these are really,
很有趣 这些模型非常非常有用
really useful, before I go to this we see these are useful to model for example
在我讲解这个之前 我们看到这两个模型能有效地模拟 比如说模拟对图像的操作
operations that we do in images. This is very useful to model real sensor
而这个模型能有效地模拟实际传感器中的噪声
noise, this is a very useful mathematical model to develop algorithms, so each one
而这个是对研究算法非常有用的数学模型
of them has it's own features and values. Lastly, I want to talk about impulse
所以这里每一个模型都有各自的特点和价值 最后 我想要讲一下脉冲噪声 (impulse noise)
noise and I can write down the formulas for these.
我可以写下它们的公式
But let me explain it with a picture, it's much easier.
但让我用图解释一下 这会简单许多
The basic idea on, on, on these type of noise, which is also called salt and
这种噪声 也叫做椒盐噪声 其基本思想是
pepper noise, is that with certain probability you change the pixel
在某个概率下 像素值完全改变
completely to a new value. And with certain other probability, you
而在另一个给定概率下
change it to a different value. For example, we start that I go over the
将其改成另外一个值 比如 我们遍历整个图像
image and with certain probability I'd change the pixel, let's say to white,
在某一概率下 像素值变为 比如白色
and with other probability I change the pixel, let's say to black and that's why
而在另一个概率下像素变为 比如说 黑色
it's called salt and pepper. If I changed it to white that's called
这就是为什么我们称其为椒盐噪声 如果像素值变成白色 那就称为盐噪声
salt, and if I changed it to black, that's called pepper.
如果变成黑色 那就称为椒噪声
So we go over the image and we change pixels with a given probability.
所以我们遍历图像 在特定概率下改变像素
It's very different than these types of noise.
这是与这些噪声非常不同的
The Gaussian noise will affect every pixel in the image.
高斯噪声会影响到图像中的每个像素
The salt and pepper will affect some more, some not, but when it effects, it
而椒盐对有些像素会影响很大 而有些完全没有影响 但是当它产生影响时
effects all of them in the same, in the same fashion.
它的影响程度是相同的
Turns them either white or turns them black with a different probabilities, so
我们将某些像素值变成白色或在另一个概率下将它们变成黑色
it's a different characteristic. You can think about this noise, for
因此这是一个不同的特性 大家可以把这个噪声看作是
example, a noise to model when the probability is very low, actually sensors
比如 当传感器以一个很低的概率出故障时 所产生的噪声
defect. If one part one pixel in your camera is
又比如 当相机中的某个部分 某个像素 烧毁了
actually burn for example you don't get signal there.
那里就没有信号了
So that's kind of a pepper noise, it might be black so with, hopefully, very
这个部分可能会变成黑色 所以是一种胡椒噪声
low probability, if your camera is a good camera, you get a pixel which is black
如果你的相机质量很好 那么出现黑色像素点
and that's a pepper noise. Okay?
即椒噪声的概率是相当低的
So these are very, very useful noise that we can see.
我们可以看出 这些是非常有用的噪声
Now, what we're going to see next is how do we estimate this types of noise that's
我们接下来要了解 如何估计这些噪声
going to be very important. It's going to be the topic of one of the
这是非常重要的 这会是下一个视频的主题
forthcoming videos. See you next.
下次见
Thank you.
谢谢大家